all right so we're gonna do why do
plants make medicine yeah does that even
make sense as a question yeah why do
plants make this I love this question
first of all it doesn't sound like it
makes any sense because first plants
aren't really making medicine they're
making molecules that we use for things
but it seems like perhaps the molecules
that the plants are using in their own
physiological processes are turning out
to be medicine and that's actually not
what's happening medicines that we find
in nature are typically secondary
compounds in plants which means that
inside the plant they serve no useful
function what they do is they dissuade
animals from consuming those plants so
these plants are for whatever reason
much better at creative chemistry than
animals are and plants effectively
evolutionarily experiment with the
production of poisons and those poisons
cause divorce to have to move on they
either can consume none of a plant or
have to consume limited amounts and then
move on to some other plant in order to
tolerate the level of toxicity but what
this means is that plants discover
molecules that interact with animal
physiology and they produce them for
precisely that reason what does it mean
to interact with animal physiology in a
way that could dissuade an animal from
eating a plant
well it means figuring out how animals
regulate their own processes and
interfering with those processes in such
a way that the animal is disrupted now
if you think about what that means what
what is it to be disrupted every system
in the body is regulated by feedbacks so
that for example the pH in your blood
your temperature all of the things that
are important to functioning are
monitored by some system and as they
move out of range in one direction there
bumped back in the other direction by
some set of feedbacks well poisons
interact with those regulatory processes
and so the reason that we find so many
honest-to-goodness medicines in nature
is that what it is to be sick to be
diseased is to have something
dysregulated and plants have
experimented with the chemistry and
they've found ways to intervene in all
of these systems and so if you have a
system in which your dysregulated low
it's very likely that there's a plant
out of there that has found a molecule
that will push that system in the high
direction and therefore the key to
taking a poison and turning it into a
medicine is finding the right molecule
for a particular kind of dysregulation
and titrating it so you get just enough
to bump you back into the the useful
range so plants really are making
medicine but they're doing so because
medicines are toxins and we use them
productively because we understand the
systems on how to intervene in those
systems in many cases but the plants are
producing them for a hospital purpose
and then we are caught but plants also
rely on animals to propagate certain
plants so like that that's how we get
sugars and vitamins that are beneficial
to systems well plants have complex
relationships with animals typically the
animals you're talking about are either
pollinators or fruit distributors and
fruits are tremendously non-toxic for
the most part except where a plant has
an interest in one creature distributing
a seed and not another so there are
plants that for example contain toxins
for mammals there are small fruits that
are distributed by birds that mammals
can
eat the reason that this is occurring is
that from a plant's perspective a bird
is often a much better distributor
especially where there are no forgivers
bats if you have to choose between
terrestrial mammals and flying birds
flying birds are obviously capable of
distributing seeds much farther afield
and so sometimes plants will intervene
by introducing something that's
unpalatable to to mammals one very
interesting case is actually the Chili
Peppers Chili Peppers have a compound in
them that triggers the mammalian damage
sensors it actually doesn't do physical
damage but it triggers the body's
monitoring apparatus for that damage
which leaves those Chili Peppers on the
plant to be distributed by birds who are
much more effective at spreading their
seeds so they are it's a
neurotransmitter mimic that the Chili
Peppers have in them that causes that
sensation of burning which is not
actually an indication of damage and
that is there to intervene in the
competition between birds and mammals in
favor of the birds so do you think that
there's a higher distribution of what we
consider what the plant would consider a
toxin and what we might consider it
medicine and core functioning parts of
the planet like a fruit isn't
necessarily core to the individual plant
survival it's more about the propagation
of the species so would there be more
toxins in the bark or a root system
click on you would expect the places
that have the highest concentration of
toxins that we would then use as
medicines to be those tissues that are
either most likely to be eaten or most
valuable if they are lost and this is in
fact what we see so around here we have
an invasive species foxglove from which
the heart drug do
Tallis has taken and digitalis is
concentrated in the leaves of the
foxglove plant rather than the flowers
which are very short-lived so the plant
has a lot more to lose by losing a piece
of leaf tissue with which it's
collecting sunlight rather than a flower
that happens to be available at the
moment but will only be blooming for a
week or two so yes we should expect and
in fact we do see a concentration of
these molecules in vulnerable valuable
parts of the plant
whereas fruits are designed to be
expendable fruits are an enticement or
what we call fruits there are lots of
fruits that you wouldn't recognize as
delicious but when you say further than
you're talking about the delicious type
of fruit those fruits are rewards for an
animal distributor to take the seeds
elsewhere and yes it would expect either
no toxicity or toxicity that works in
favor of some distributors and against
others towards weibo thorns what about
for us what about thorns I like that
that's a that seems like a defense
mechanism that's is this is no longer
we're not talking about a medicine
there's no beneficiary of thorns unless
we made some sort of bird no there
aren't well bird is a good example there
are many cases that I can think of in
tropical species especially in which
thorns block one route of access to
fruits leaving those fruits available to
creatures that come a different way so
for example there are palm fruits in
neotropical forests which are which
exists on palms with extremely spiky
trunks that could not be climbed by a
rodent for example but they can be
accessed by kinkajous which leap from
canopy to canopy and so kinky trees are
actually decent distributors because
they're pretty wide-ranging it's a
fairly large
mammal and so a poem that that stacks
the deck in favor of a kinkajou which
can hang by its prehensile tail and
access the fruits in the canopy and
against rodents makes a lot of sense and
give it a little time it wouldn't be
hard to come up with a dozen examples
like that where the thorns are actually
a way of intervening in competition
between different animal taxa you said
that plants experiment it's almost like
it's almost like anthropomorphizing
bench yes yeah well this is a this is a
problem that evolutionary biologists are
constantly stuck in which is we all
understand that the plants aren't
intentionally experimenting for example
but to say things in a way that is
perfectly rigorous with respect to the
absence of consciousness from the
process is so cumbersome and so hard for
people to follow that we default into a
kind of shorthand where we say things
like the plant is experimenting because
what is what it is doing is tantamount
to experimenting the easiest way to
understand it is that it is
experimenting but experimenting is a
fairly precise analogy to what it's
actually doing it's doing a bunch of
things and then those things that
provide a benefit stick and so nature is
experimenting even though nature isn't a
it's not even a creature
you